<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dajsiepoznac2017 on kars7e&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>http://blog.kars7e.io/tags/dajsiepoznac2017/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dajsiepoznac2017 on kars7e&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.kars7e.io/tags/dajsiepoznac2017/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Project details for filesyncer</title>
      <link>http://blog.kars7e.io/2017/03/17/Project-details-for-filesyncer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2017 01:31:17 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kars7e.io/2017/03/17/Project-details-for-filesyncer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve became a huge fan of describing ideas using single sentence. If you can&amp;rsquo;t describe an idea this way, it may be that this idea needs more thought or it&amp;rsquo;s too complex and could be divided into smaller components (the latter is rare). Let me describe my project for this year&amp;rsquo;s edition of &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.kars7e.io/2017/03/12/Daj-Si%C4%99-pozna%C4%87---challange-accepted-again/&#34;&gt;DSP contest&lt;/a&gt; using single sentence then:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An application that continously runs on a computer, &lt;strong&gt;monitors for changes in selected path&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;communicates these changes to other instances&lt;/strong&gt; of the same application running on different computers connected together in &lt;strong&gt;single L2 network&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, I did it. I hope it conveys something meaningful to you. Of course, this is still very vague and, depending on the person who reads it, could be visualised as simple rsync running in daemon mode as well as very sophisticated distributed file system. Let me further clarify by providing some simple use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feature-requirements&#34;&gt;Feature requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short list of features I would like to have, ordered by increasing complexity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once executed, application runs continously, until user stops it using ctrl-C combination (or it receives TERM signal some other way).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application should take an argument which is a path to a directory on local filesystem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application should monitor the specified directory by registering any changes to any files/subdirectories in that directory. Specifically, it should register new file or directory being created, existing file/directory being deleted, existing file or directory being renamed (why rename is a separate requirement I will write on a different occasion), and existing file&amp;rsquo;s content being modified.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application should be able to detect other instances of itself running in the same network by using network broadcasting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application should share the changes it detects with other instances of itself running in the same network.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application should listen for changes coming from other instances of itself&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application should apply changes coming from other instances of itself to it&amp;rsquo;s local state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will stop here. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem like a lot of requirements, especially given that I won&amp;rsquo;t spend too much time veryfing if these features have been implemented correctly. &lt;strong&gt;The main goal here is to deliver MVP&lt;/strong&gt;, and the challenge is using language knew to me to achieve that MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-more-thing-rust-installation&#34;&gt;One more thing - rust installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to produce another introductory post again, so let&amp;rsquo;s document some work. This will be trivial, but&amp;hellip; you have to start somewhere. I&amp;rsquo;m using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rust-lang.org&#34;&gt;Rust programming language&lt;/a&gt;, which means I should have installed on my system. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it then. I&amp;rsquo;m using MacOS, and de facto a standard &lt;a href=&#34;https://brew.sh/&#34;&gt;package manager&lt;/a&gt; for MacOS. Rust installation couldn&amp;rsquo;t be simpler:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #ffffff&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ brew install rust
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Which after a minute or so gives us &lt;code&gt;rustc&lt;/code&gt; command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #ffffff&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ rustc --help
Usage: rustc &lt;span style=&#34;color: #333333&#34;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;OPTIONS&lt;span style=&#34;color: #333333&#34;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; INPUT

Options:
    -h --help           Display this message
    --cfg SPEC          Configure the compilation environment
    .
    .
    .
    &lt;span style=&#34;color: #888888&#34;&gt;# Omitted&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s finish this post with simple, classic and mandatory &amp;ldquo;Hello world&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #ffffff&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color: #008800; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;fn&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color: #0066BB; font-weight: bold&#34;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;()&lt;span style=&#34;color: #bbbbbb&#34;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;{&lt;span style=&#34;color: #bbbbbb&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style=&#34;color: #bbbbbb&#34;&gt;    &lt;/span&gt;println&lt;span style=&#34;color: #333333&#34;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;background-color: #fff0f0&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;Hello, world!&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;);&lt;span style=&#34;color: #bbbbbb&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
}&lt;span style=&#34;color: #bbbbbb&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;that we compile with &lt;code&gt;rustc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34; style=&#34;background: #ffffff&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;line-height: 125%&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ rustc main.rs
$ ./main
Hello, world!
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! Environment ready. I will follow up in the next post, where I will attempt to write a daemon that handles signals gracefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: I&amp;rsquo;m learning Rust as I write these posts. Hence, there will be a lot of modifications and sudden changes of course in my code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daj Się poznać - challenge accepted (again)</title>
      <link>http://blog.kars7e.io/2017/03/12/Daj-Si%C4%99-pozna%C4%87---challange-accepted-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://blog.kars7e.io/2017/03/12/Daj-Si%C4%99-pozna%C4%87---challange-accepted-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago (or one year ago to be more accurate) I &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.kars7e.io/2016/02/12/daj-sie-poznac-challange-accepted/&#34;&gt;decided to take up a challange&lt;/a&gt; of DSP contest. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t much of a success (to put it mildly). I&amp;rsquo;ve been very reluctant to try it again, but finally, few hours before the registration closed, I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://uczestnicy.dajsiepoznac.pl/lista&#34;&gt;signed up&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m going to give some details here what was my thought process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dsp-in-short&#34;&gt;DSP in short&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSP, or Daj Się poznać, is a coding competition, but very different from what one may expect from something called a &amp;ldquo;coding competition.&amp;rdquo; There is no solving of algorithmic challenges, or doing that in most optimal an elegant way (but it may be part of your work!). Instead, the goal is to actually &lt;strong&gt;deliver&lt;/strong&gt;. Write two posts/week, push code to your repo. The quality of the code doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter (for real!). DSP promotes two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;participants. yes, competition title says &amp;ldquo;Get noticed!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GET THINGS DONE&lt;/strong&gt; - stop producing flashes in the pan, but actually deliver!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-haven-t-been-done&#34;&gt;Things haven&amp;rsquo;t been done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, to put it mildly. If you look at my blog history and check the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.kars7e.io/tags/dajsiepoznac2016/&#34;&gt;dajsiepoznac2016&lt;/a&gt; tag, you will immediately spot the problem. Three posts out of required 20. Don&amp;rsquo;t even try looking at the GitHub repo - you won&amp;rsquo;t find anything useful there. Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good question. I did a quick retrospection, and came up with following conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a busy man&lt;/strong&gt;. My family, my beautiful wife and daughter, take a lot of my time. My work projects naturally take up most of my weekdays. I also play basketball as many times as I can. All of this leaves me barely any time to work on my side projects. I was not able to dedicate enough time I planned, and the moment I realized I&amp;rsquo;m not able to keep up with my planned DSP work, my motivation went out the window.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I tried to do too much&lt;/strong&gt;. My project ( an online game) was way too big for this type of competition. DSP is about delivering, and the smaller project, the greater chance is that you will deliver. Some people submitted already undergoing projects to the contest, and they often barely made it (or didn&amp;rsquo;t) to the end.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I cared too much&lt;/strong&gt;. It sounds completely counterintuitive, so let me explain. When planning my work and visualizing it in my head, I&amp;rsquo;ve included all the items a production-ready project must include, like tests, scalability, clean code, proper design, etc., etc. It sounds ridiculous,  doesn&amp;rsquo;t it? It does to me know, but back then I &lt;strong&gt;cared too much&lt;/strong&gt;. I wanted to create a perfect project, and again, DSP is NOT about that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can I do about it to improve the situation in my second attempt?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deliver-deliver-deliver&#34;&gt;Deliver, deliver, deliver!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pretty sure this mantra was a part of many talks/presentations/coaching books. But this is also my plan. With following details:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced scope&lt;/strong&gt; - I decided to learn myself some rust, which I wanted to do for very long time. My project will be a simple file sync tool, think poor man&amp;rsquo;s dropbox. But very poor man, penniless I daresay. With no clothes. And he owes $2M for God knows what. No UI, no graphics, no advanced features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minimize the burden&lt;/strong&gt; - No tests, clean code as much as I do by default. Design? It will come up naturally or will be a result of refactoring (the project is small!). One of the things that I will have to decide on is how to resolve conflicts when syncing files. Or will I? I can just ignore it and, for example, take the latest file version, which is the simplest (and probably incorrect) way to solve it. Whatever it takes to &lt;strong&gt;deliver&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t try to predict everything upfront&lt;/strong&gt; - yes, my biggest problem. Works perfectly well in my daily job (I can save us months of work by spending a week on analyzing stuff). But this is not the place, and I need to give up this attitude.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, I feel motivated. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>